<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jhyoussef.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jhyoussef.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-30T01:47:52+00:00</updated><id>https://jhyoussef.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Off the Fossil Record</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">On Writing</title><link href="https://jhyoussef.github.io/blog/2025/On-Writing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Writing"/><published>2025-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhyoussef.github.io/blog/2025/On%20Writing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhyoussef.github.io/blog/2025/On-Writing/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="been-a-while-crocodile">Been a while, crocodile</h3> <p>When I work at some physical task (at this point in my life, primarily cleaning or working on art commissions), I imagine what I would write. Usually, it involves some overintellectualizing…something that feels poignant. More often, I am coming up with ideas. Playing with themes I want to explore, but that never quite manifest. For instance:</p> <ul> <li>Why paleontology?</li> <li>Dissecting the concept of evolutionary success: what does it mean for an organism, species, or lineage to be “successful,” and how thinking about life in such a manner may contribute to both 1) arbitrary valuation of some life over others and 2) reciprocally reinforce some flawed application of concepts of biological success to human individuals?</li> <li>How do we visually and conceptually represent evolution? through time, through space, with trees, etc.? What connotations come with each form?</li> <li>On “Dragons”, et al.: Pterosaurs, <em>Microraptor</em>, and <em>Yi Qi</em></li> <li>Why academia?</li> <li>Is there room for infinite growth (biologically?) Is there an upper-cap for species richness?</li> <li>How can I justify paleontology?</li> <li>How can I go into academia?</li> <li>The Anthropocene, the sixth extinction, and the far future.</li> <li>At the end of the world, will we realize that we cannot eat money?</li> </ul> <p>As you may be able to see, reader, there’s some ideas that remain consistent. How do we engage with paleontology, biology, and nature? What am I doing this for?</p> <p>I began this website with the intent of it becoming a formal academic blog. My thoughts on the new <em>Nanotyrannus</em> discourse. A comment on the new filter-feeding pterosaur from Brazil, sister to <em>Pterodaustro</em>. Each work (a way, also, to practice writing), becomes an essay. An essay becomes something stressful that needs to be perfect and refined. So, as you may have noticed, nothing gets posted at all.</p> <p>But I still want to add something. I still feel that I have things to say - and so this blog will probably be something a little bit more freeform. Because, otherwise, I think I will never write at all.</p> <p>I adore paleontology. But I also am someone who studied more than just biology - I am just as inseparable from astronomy, religious history, and art. I experience paleontology through those lenses, and likewise, existing as I am, experience the world through paleontology. It is impossible, I think, for me to disentangle them.</p> <p>Impossible to forget the courses I have taken on habitability, geobiology and earth history when I read about the newest climate report. Impossible to forget the sorrow of lost culture and information when I read about lost species. Impossible to forget what I know about biology and statistics when I see manipulations of data on the public stage.</p> <p>So … rather than trying to think of the perfect things to say, I’ll add my voice to the void, and engage with topics that feel meaningful to me, through the only lenses I know. And, the next time I’m thinking about what I should write, I’ll simply begin.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="introductory"/><category term="comments"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Starting, and some topics and themes I'd like to cover]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Launching Off the Fossil Record!</title><link href="https://jhyoussef.github.io/blog/2025/testing-out-the-format/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Launching Off the Fossil Record!"/><published>2025-08-31T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-31T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jhyoussef.github.io/blog/2025/testing-out-the-format</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jhyoussef.github.io/blog/2025/testing-out-the-format/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="welcome">Welcome!</h1> <p>Hi! My name is Julia Youssef, and I must say, working with the editor I am currently using might be the death of me, so excuse any typos in these first few posts…</p> <p>I am a recent graduate from the University of Chicago, where I studied geosciences and nearly completed most of the astrophysics major before realizing I prefer working with the deep past underground than in the skies (though, I am often asked if I work with “space dinosaurs…”). I also spent a lot of my spare time (and electives) working on my art skills and cultivating my interests in philosophy of science as well as religion in classical antiquity. Now, I am still doing research – in this awkward space between undergrad and a hopeful PhD – and trying to grapple with the role paleontology has in our daily lives, society, and, well, my own academic trajectory. Hence, …I wanted to set up this site, write about my thoughts and relationship to UChicago, geosciences, astrophysics, biology, and art.</p> <p>If you are curious about topics like paleoart, how we reconstruct ancient organisms, or how we engage with deep time, you’ll find posts here. Or, if you’re interested in bigger questions – how we define evolutionary “success,” where we fit on the tree of life, and how we feel about those relationships – that’s here, too. And since I wasn’t born into a family of academics, I’ll write about how I feel about higher education, how I balance art, science, and identity, and how I try to move forward.</p> <p>Oh - and occasionally I’ll air my grievances about obscure papers or fawn over the newest discoveries on niche clades (with a special fondness for <em>Nyctosauridae</em> and <em>Anurognathidae</em>, both pterosaurs, and some mammalian lineages).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/film-field-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/film-field-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/film-field-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/film-field.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/pano-wyoming-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/pano-wyoming-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/pano-wyoming-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/pano-wyoming.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Me in Wyoming with Professor Sereno's Dinosaur Science course! </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="paleontology"/><category term="introductory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Blog introduction and greeting and who the hell am I]]></summary></entry></feed>